Guide to the Bernard Green Collection BCMS.0013
Brooklyn Collection
Bernard Green Collection
1932-1972
Brooklyn Collection
Green, Bernard, 1908-1975
BCMS.0013
0.2 Linear feet in 1 half-size document box
This collection consists of correspondence, photographs, ephemera and sheet music belonging to New York composer, conductor, and arranger Bernard Green. The bulk is correspondence related to a book Green had hoped to publish, but which he never completed.
Biographical Note
Bernard "Bernie" Green was born in New York on September 14, 1908. His family name was Greenberg, but he used the name Green professionally, and was known to most friends and associates as "Bernie". Green received a music degree from the New York University College of Fine Arts in 1932 and worked principally in music, as a composer, conductor, and arranger for film, radio and television. He became widely known in the 1940s, when he earned a headlining spot on the Henry Morgan radio show. His better-known credits include the television shows "Mr. Peepers" and "Caesar's Hour". Green also worked in other facets of the show-business industry, recording albums, writing columns for the Brooklyn Daily Eagle, The New York Times, and the International Musician, promoting fellow musicians like Les Brown, and writing comedy scripts.
In his later years, Green began preparations for a book he hoped to publish. He envisioned a collection of anecdotes by celebrities (many of whom he knew personally) about their mothers, and sent out letters requesting material from comedians, actresses, scientists, politicians, and other notable people. The replies he received make up much of this collection. The project was never completed, however, and Green died at the age of 66 at his home in Westport, Connecticut, on August 10, 1975.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the Bernard Green collection is correspondence. Green was in the exploratory stages of writing a book of favorite stories by notable people about their mothers, and much of the correspondence relates to that project. Other highlights from the collection include a program from the "roasting" of Ed Sullivan by the Friars Club, sheet music, and a scrapbook of Green's column in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle.
Access
Collection is located in the Brooklyn Collection at the Central Branch at Grand Army Plaza. The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan. Requests to view the collection must be made at least 48 hours in advance of visit.
Provenance
The Bernard Green Collection was donated to the Brooklyn Public Library by the daughter-in-law of Mr. Green, Janice Greenberg.
Related Materials
Sheet Music Collection
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series by format. Within each series, the arrangement is chronological.
Arts, Modern -- 20th Century; Composers; Composers -- United States -- Correspondence; Music; Sheet music
- Series I: Correspondence, 1934-1972
  - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Two letters from Walter Winchell.
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Two letters in reference to Lionel Hampton from Fiorello LaGuardia and Stan Shaw.
    Three letters in reference to RCA Manufacturing Company from Margaret Hartigan and Herb Hendler.
    One letter from publication The International Musician.
    One letter from Columbia Recording Corporation regarding composer/arranger Les Brown.
    One undated letter from "Les", presumably Les Brown.
  - Correspondence, c. 1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Four letters from Sid Garfinkel.
  - Correspondence, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Five letters from Joe Glaser.
    One letter from Roy Topper, mentioning Joe Glaser.
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letters from celebrities in response to a request by Green. He was trying to compile material for a collection of favorite stories by notable people about their mothers, which he hoped to publish. Listing: Borge, Victor; Crosby, Bing; Dangerfield, Rodney; Ernst, Morris L. (4 letters); Farley, James A.; Glenn, John; Goldwater, Barry; Goodman, Andrew; Josefsberg, Milt (2 pages); Kazan, Elia; Lyons, Leonard; Paley, William S.; Pine, Arthur; Reed, Rex; Rockefeller, Nelson A. - letter from Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Mother); Rubinstein, Arthur; Salk, Jonas; Silvers, Phil; Styne, Julie; Sullivan, Ed (2 pages); Thomas, Lowell; Wilson, Earl; Wouk, Herman; Zanuck, Darryl
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letters written on behalf of notable individuals who declined Green's request for a story about their mothers. Listing: Bing, Rudolf – Written by Mary Dake Smith; Bundeskanzleramt – Written in German by Hubinger; Cronkite, Walter – written by Carolyn Dorsett; Ford, Henry II – written by Mott B. Heath; Gabor, Zsa Zsa – Written by Marilyn Reiss; Graham, Billy – Written by Martha Warkentin; Hoover, Edgar – written by Helen W. Gandy; Lindsay, John – Written by Thomas B. Morgan; Nixon, Richard – Written by Roland L. Elliott (2 pages); Reagan, Ronald – Written by James E. Jenkins; Roosevelt, Franklin Delano Jr. – written by Merle H. Lambert; Sabin, Albert B. – written by Ilana Brand; Shepard, Alan B., Jr. – written by John E. McLeaish; Sinatra, Frank – Written by Jim Mahoney; Trudeau, Pierre – Written by Henry Alan Lawless
- Series II: Photographs, c.1939-1965
  - Photographs, 1939-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Ten photographs, most undated, of Bernard Green with friends, family and colleagues.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Seven photographs of Bernard Green with friends, family and colleagues. Also includes promotional shots of unidentified women, and a cast shot of the Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet.
- Series III: Ephemera, 1932-1968
  - Scrapbook, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Scrapbook of clippings from Green's "Penned Portraits" column in the Brooklyn Daily Eagle.
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Items relating to collaboration between Bernard Green and Eli Lloyd Hoffman. Sanford's Restaurant "menu-ette", newspaper clipping, and radio play script co-authored by Green and Hoffman.
  - Friars' Club Program, March 15, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Program for Friars Club "roast" of Ed Sullivan at the Waldorf Astoria. Includes anecdotes from fellow entertainers, images of Friars Club members and celebrities, and advertisements.
  - "Night of the Century" Salute to the U.S.O. Program, February 11, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Program from opening event at Madison Square Garden. Includes features on U.S.O. entertainers, (e.g., Bob Hope and Bing Crosby) and promotional copy on the design and building of Madison Square Garden.
- Series IV: Sheet Music, 1941-1949
  - Sheet music for two songs by Bernard Green
    "I was an April Fool" (Lyric by Bernie Green, Music by Doug Watt)
    "Twenty Questions" (by Moe Jaffe, Dick Hardt and Bernie Green)
    Note: These items are stored with the Sheet Music Collection, Brooklyn Collection Annex, Shelf 1.2.